Guide to the Malet Family Papers, 1808-1937
Malet Family papers 1808-1937
Malet family
15 Linear Feet 7,000 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of the Malet family were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library of Duke University between 1970 and 1990.
Succession of the Malet Baronetage
Sir Charles Warre Malet, 1st Baronet
1752, Dec. 30 Baptised
1791, Feb. 24 Was created a baronet
1799, Sept. 23 Married Susanna Wales
1815, Dec. 15 Died and was succeeded by son Alexander Malet
Sir Alexander Malet, 2nd Baronet
1800, July 23 Born
1834, Dec. 22 Married Marian Dora Spalding (d. 1891, Jan. 2)
1886, Nov. 28 Died and was succeeded by son Henry Charles Eden Malet
Sir Henry Charles Eden Malet, 3rd Baronet
1835, Sept. 25 Born
1873, Feb. 19 Married Laura Jane Hamilton (d. 1922, May 9)
1904, Jan 12 Died and was succeeded by brother Edward Baldwin Malet
Sir Edward Baldwin Malet, 4th Baronet
1837, Oct. 10 Born
1885, Mar. 19 Married Lady Ermyntrude Sackville Russell (d. 1927, Mar. 22)
1908, June 29 Died and was succeeded by cousin Edward St. Lo Malet
Biographical Notes
Sir Charles Warre Malet, 1st Baronet
1753? Born
1785-1791 Resident minister at Poona, India
1791 Was created a baronet for his services at Poona, India
1791-1798 Acting Governor of Bombay
1798 Retired and returned to England
1815 Died
Sir Alexander Malet, 2nd Baronet
1800, June Born at Hartham Park, Wiltshire
1815 Succeeded to baronetcy
1822 BA, Christ Church, Oxford
1824 Entered diplomatic service as attaché at St. Petersburg
1832-1834 Secretary of Legation at Lisbon under Lord Howden
1834 Married Marian Dora Spalding
1836-1843 Secretary of the Embassy at the Hague
1849 Became Minister Plenipotentiary to the Germanic confederation at Frankfurt
1860 Author of The Conquest of England
1866 Retired
1870 Author of The Overthrow of the German Confederation by Prussia in 1866
1886, Nov. 28 Died in London
Marian Dora Spalding, Lady Malet
Unknown Born to Thomas Spalding and Mary Anne Eden
1834, Dec. 22 Married Sir Alexander Malet
1835 Gave birth to Sir Henry Charles Eden Malet, 3rd Baronet
1836 Anonymously published Violet, or The Danseuse: A Portraiture of Human Passions and Character, a satirical novel
ca. 1836 Became friends with Queen Sophia of Holland, with whom she corresponded until the Queen's death in 1877
1837, Oct. 10 Gave birth to Sir Edward Baldwin Malet, 4th Baronet
1891, Jan. 2 Died
Sir Henry Charles Eden Malet, 3rd Baronet
1835 Born to Sir Alexander Malet and Marian Dora (Spalding) Malet
1854 Commissioned in the Grenadier Guards
1854-1856 Served in the Crimean War
1862 Was promoted to Lieutenant Colonel
1870 Retired
1904 Died
Sir Edward Malet
1837, Oct. 10 Born to Marian and Alexander Malet
1854 Appointed attaché at Frankfurt at age seventeen
1860 Appointed to the British Legation at Parana in the Argentine
1861 Transferred to Brazil
1862 Changed positions with William Brodie, attaché at Washington, D.C.
1864 Returned to England as Head of Chancery
1865 Transferred to Constantinople
1867 Transferred to Paris
1871 Promoted to Secretary of Legation at Peking
1873 Accepted appointment as Secretary of the Athens Legation and transferred to Greece
1875 Accepted appointment as Secretary of the Rome Legation and moved to Italy
1876 Promoted to Secretary of Embassy
1878 Appointed to Constantinople
1879 Appointed Agent and Consul General in Egypt and transferred to Alexandria
1883 Promoted to Minister at Brussels and transferred to Belgium
1884 Appointed to Berlin as ambassador
1885 Married Ermyntrude Hastings
1895 Retired and returned to England
1901 Published Shifting Scenes
1908, June Died at the Chorleywood home of his sister-in-law, Lady Ella Russell
Collection Overview
The papers of the Malet family span the dates 1808-1937, with most of the papers being dated between 1824 and 1908. The papers consist chiefly of correspondence among members of the Malet family, particularly Sir Charles Warre Malet, Sir Alexander Malet and his wife Lady Marian Dora Malet, Sir Henry Charles Eden Malet, and Sir Edward Baldwin Malet, and their friends and diplomatic associates. Notable correspondents include Queen Sophia of the Netherlands, Sidney Herbert, Lord Clarendon, Lord Napier, Lord Stuart de Rochesay, Lord Brougham, Sir Rennell Rodd, Lord Lyons, Lord Granville and Lord Dufferin. The papers also include printed material, writings, financial papers, clippings, photographs, Lady Marian Dora Malet's diary (1831-1833), Sir Henry Charles Eden Malet's album of illustrations of his service in the Crimean War, and miscellaneous papers. The collection is particularly rich in material concerning 19th-century British diplomacy. The letters of Sir Alexander and Sir Edward Malet thoroughly document British relations with Russia, Portugal, Holland, Austria, Germany, the United States, France, Turkey, Greece, Italy, Belgium, China, and Egypt. The letters and album of Sir Henry Charles Eden Malet in the Malet Family Correspondence Series provide detailed information about the Crimean War, particularly the siege of Sevastopol.
The Queen Sophia Series contains around 900 letters (1842-1877) from Queen Sophia of the Netherlands to Lady Malet relating to political and diplomatic matters with references to Emperor Napoleon III, Empress Eugénie, and Prince Napoleon, of France; King William II, King William III, and Queen Anna, of the Netherlands; King William I and Queen Olga of Württemberg; Francis Napier, Baron Napier; Edward Henry Stanley, Earl of Derby; George William Frederick Villiers, Earl of Clarendon; Henry Richard Charles Wellesley, Earl Cowley; and to other members of the royal families of England, France, the Netherlands, and Württemberg.
In the Alexander and Edward Malet Correspondence Series, Sir Alexander Malet's letters to his mother chronicle his duty in Russia (1824-1827), Portugal (1833-1835), Holland (1836-1843), and Austria and Germany (1844-1845). Three letterbooks contain copies of dispatches that he wrote to the Foreign Office while acting as envoy to the Germanic Confederation at Frankfurt from 1852-1866. Bismarck, a friend of the family, was at Frankfurt between 1851 and 1858, and conversations with him were reported in the correspondence.
The letters of Sir Edward Malet in the Alexander and Edward Malet Correspondence Series cover his entire diplomatic career. He was in Washington, D.C. during the American Civil War, in Paris during the Franco-Prussian War and Commune, in Constantinople at the end of the Russo-Turkish War, and in Egypt as agent and consul-general from 1879-1883. Peking (1873), Athens (1874), Rome (1875-1876), Brussels (1884), and Berlin (1884-1895) were also on his tour of duty. One volume contains copies of Malet's dispatches from Egypt from 1881-1883. Around 4,000 letters span his career, documenting political events of the period.
The Malet Family Printed Material Series includes material concerning the marriage of Princess Louise of Schleswig-Holstein in 1891 and for the visit on that occasion of the Emperor and Empress of Germany. The Alexander and Edward Malet Writings Series includes Sir Edward's Shifting Scenes (1901) in both print and manuscript format and proofs and manuscripts of Sir Alexander's The Overthrow of the Germanic Federations by Prussia in 1866 (1870)
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Crimean War, 1853-1856
Derby, Edward Henry Stanley, Earl of, 1826-1893
Diplomats -- Great Britain -- Correspondence
England -- Kings and rulers
Europe -- Politics and government 18th century
France -- Kings and rulers
Germany -- Kings and rulers
Great Britain; --Army.--Grenadier Guards
Great Britain -- Politics and government 1837-1901
India -- History -- British occupation, 1767-1945
Netherlands -- Kings and rulers
Eden, Frances, dd 1801-1849
Malet, Alexander, Sir, 1800-1886
Malet, Edwin, Sir, 1837-1908
Malet, Henry Charles Eden, Sir
Malet, Mary Ann Dora Spalding -- Lady, d. 1891
Sophie, Queen Consort of William III, King of the Netherlands, 1818-1877
Contents of Collection
- Malet Family Subgroup
  - Malet Family Correspondence Series,1808-and1908and undated
    Chiefly letters to members of the Malet family. Includes letters (1850-1867) from Lord Edward Henry Stanley to Lady Marian Dora Malet concerning politics and literature; letters from Frances Eden to Lady Malet concerning her life in India from 1835-1841; letters to Sir Charles Warre Malet, Indian administrator and diplomat; and letters from Sir Henry Charles Eden Malet, 3rd Baronet, to his parents describing his life as a young officer during the Crimean War. Other correspondents include Sidney Herbert,; Lord Clarendon,; Lord Napier,; Lord and Lady Palmerston,; Sharif Pasha, and Nubar Pasha.
    Note: For more detailed description of the material in this series, see the cards in the Main Entry drawer of the card catalog. The inventory file also contains a folder of biographical and genealogical material regarding the Malet family.
    - 1808-1859, (9 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1860-1908and undated, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Malet Family Printed Material Series, 1861-1867, 1891
    Includes Sketch of the Life of the Duke of Devonshire (1861), printed political papers and programs, invitations, and other items from the ceremonies for the marriage of Princess Louise in 1891 and for the visit on that occasion of the Emperor and Empress of Germany. Also includes a warrant from Queen Victoria granting Sir Alexander Malet's diplomatic pension, Feb. 22, 1867 (oversize folder).
    Arranged chronologically.
    - 1861-1864, (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - 1891, (1 folder)
  - Malet Family Photographs Series, 1866-1883and undated
    Card photographs of Sir Edward Malet,; Lady Ermyntrude Malet,; Ahmed Araby, and Izzet Bey.
    Unarranged.
    - 1866-1883and undated, (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Lady Marian Dora Malet Diary, 1831 Nov. 14-1833 Aug. 29and1857
    Photocopy of a typescript of a two-volume diary (1831 Nov. 14 - 1833 Aug. 29) of Lady Malet written in the years before her marriage. Entries chiefly contain information about her social activities and conversations with friends, many of whom were notable political figures. Includes a sequel written by her in 1857 in which she reflects on her earlier entries and her relationships with those mentioned in the diary. This sequel concludes with an epilogue by her son, Sir Edward Malet. Some pages appear to be missing from the typescript.
    - Diary, 1831-1833, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Diary sequel,1857, (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Sir Henry Charles Eden Malet Album,1834and 1855-1856
    Album of watercolors, drawings, and maps, most created by Sir Henry Charles Eden, 3rd Baronet, during his service as a lieutenant in the Grenadier Guards during the Crimean War. Most of the 44 sketches, battle plans, and watercolors illustrate the siege of Sevastopol, the countryside, and army life. Views include Balaklava, the Inkerman Valley, and the Mackenzie Heights. The album also contains views and maps of the Redan, Mamelon, and Malakoff. Two watercolors of Cintra dated 1834 are not by Malet, if the penciled dates are correct, as he was born in 1835.
    - Album,1834, 1855-1856(1 vol.) (Oversize-box 131)
  - Queen Sophia Series, 1842-1877and undated
    Letters, clippings, and pictures representing Lady Marian (sometimes spelled Mary Anne and Marianne); Dora Malet's close friendship with Queen Sophia Frederica Mathilda of the Netherlands. Most letters are from Queen Sophia, and include references to her personal life with her husband King William III; her friendships with Lord Clarendon,; Lord Cowley,; Lord Napier, and their wives. Other English friends mentioned were Charles Villiers,; Lady Ely,; Lady Westmoreland, and Lady Russell. Letters document her anglophilia and her antipathy towards the Russians. Correspondence includes analyses of Napoleon III and his wife Empress Eugénie. Letters contain not only the Queen's information and judgments about European affairs, but also her comments and opinions about rulers, nobles, diplomats, politicians, and military men of England, France, Germany, Austria, the Netherlands, and Russia. Letters are arranged chronologically. Includes clippings regarding Queen Sophia's death in 1877 and a cabinet card photograph of the Queen at the end of the series.
    Note: Many of the letters in this series are undated. At some point, dates were penciled on letters, but many appear to be inaccurate. For more detailed description of the material in this series, see the cards in the Main Entry drawer of the card catalog. The inventory file also contains a folder of biographical and genealogical material regarding Queen Sophia.
    - Correspondence, 1842-1848, (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1849-1863, (10 folders) (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1864-1877and undated, (9 folders) (Box 5)
    - Clippings,1877, (1 folder)
    - Photograph,1877(1 item)
- Alexander and Edward Malet Subgroup
  - Correspondence Series, 1824-1908
    Correspondence among Sir Alexander Malet and Sir Edward Malet and their family members, friends, and political associates. Many of Sir Alexander's letters concern family matters, his accommodations and events at court at his various posts in Europe, and his appointments and transfers. Some letters contain information about political events in Russia, Portugal, Great Britain, and Afghanistan. Sir Edward's letters to his parents (1854-1890) include comments on British politics as well as political events and figures in other places where he traveled (Washington, D.C. during the American Civil War; Paris in 1870; and Berlin in 1884). Also included is Sir Edward's diplomatic correspondence. Correspondents include Lord Clarendon,; Lord Stuart de Rochesay,; Lord Brougham,; Lord Loftus,; Lord Powlett,; Sir J. R. Milbanke,; Sir Rennell Rodd,; Lord Lyons,; Lord Granville, the Duke of York (later King George V),; Lord Salisbury,; Wilfred Scawen Blunt,; Lord Dufferin,; Esme Howard, and Lord Palmerston. One letterbook (1855-1858) contains dispatches of Sir Alexander Malet from Frankfurt while he served as British Minister to the Germanic Federation to Foreign Secretaries, Lords Malmesbury,; John Russell and Clarendon, while five others contain printed correspondence from numerous diplomats regarding the political situation in Egypt 1882-1884 and 1904.
    Letters are arranged chronologically with letterbooks arranged chronologically at the end of the series.
    - Correspondence, 1824-1836, (8 folders) (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1837-1854, (7 folders) (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1855-1866, (9 folders) (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1867-1871 Apr. 19, (6 folders) (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1871 Apr.20-1871 Dec.and undated, (5 folders) (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1872 Jan.-1874, (5 folders) (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1875-1878, (6 folders) (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, 1879-1880 Apr., (4 folders) (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, 1880 May-1882 July, (6 folders) (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, 1882 Aug.-Dec.1883, (5 folders) (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1884-1886, (6 folders) (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1887-1891, (6 folders) (Box 17)
    - Correspondence, 1892-1899, (7 folders) (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, 1900-1908May and undated, (5 folders) (Box 19)
    - Letterbooks of Sir Alexander Malet's Dispatches to the Foreign Office, 1852-1858(2 vols.) (Box 20)
    - Letterbooks of Sir Alexander Malet's Dispatches to the Foreign Office, 1859-1864(2 vols.) (Box 21)
    - Correspondence concerning Egypt, 1878-1884, (1 folder) (Box 22)
    - Despatch to Her Majesty's Agent and Consul-General at Cairo Respecting the Affairs of Egypt, 1882, (1 vol.)
    - Correspondence Respecting the Affairs of Egypt, 1882, (1 vol.) (Box 23)
    - Further Correspondence Respecting the Affairs of Egypt, 1883, (1 vol.)
    - Further Correspondence Respecting the Reorganization of Egypt, 1884, (1 vol.)
    - Reports by His Majesty's Agent and Consul-General on the Finances, Administration, and Condition of Egypt and the Soudan in 1904, 1905, (1 vol.)
  - Writings Series, 1863-1901and undated
    Writings include manuscripts and proofs of Sir Alexander Malet's book The Overthrow of the Germanic Confederation by Prussia in 1866 (1870) and manuscripts and a copy of Sir Edward Malet's Shifting Scenes ( 1901). Fragments of poetry, songs, and playbills written by the Malets are also contained within this series, as well as a small illustrated manuscript pamphlet entitled The Countess and the Tomahawk.
    - The Overthrow of the Germanic Federations by Prussia in1866, by Sir Alexander Malet,1870, (manuscript, 2 folders) (Box 24)
    - The Overthrow of the Germanic Federations by Prussia in 1866, by Sir Alexander Malet,1870, (proof, 4 folders)
    - The Overthrow of the Germanic Federations by Prussia in 1866, by Sir Alexander Malet,1870(proof, 1 folder) (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, 1863-1883and undated, (1 folder)
    - Shifting Scenes, by Sir Edward Malet,1901, (manuscript, 2 folders)
    - Shifting Scenes, by Sir Edward Malet,1901, (1 vol.) (Box 26)
  - Printed Material Series, 1849-1907and undated
    Volumes, printed reports, playbills, advertisements, menus, calling cards, membership lists of organizations, and guest lists documenting the social and diplomatic activities of Sir Alexander and Sir Edward Malet. Includes a program with seating arrangements for the wedding of Princess Louise of Schleswig-Holstein, a 1905 biographical pamphlet on Sir Edward Malet, and 2 copies of a 1907 pamphlet entitled The Episode of the Egyptian Rebellion of 1882.
    - The Secret History of the English Occupation of Egypt, by Wilfred Scawen Blunt,1895, (1 vol.) (Box 26)
    - Printed Material, 1849-1907, (3 folders)
    - Les notes sommaire et généale sur les charges relevées par l'accusation contre Ahmed Araby, 1882, (1 vol.) (Box 27)
    - Les actes et protocoles concernant le litage entre L'Allemagne, La France, et La Grande Bretagne d'une part et Le Japon d'autre part, 1905, (1 vol.)
  - Financial Papers Series, 1824-1907
    Receipts, hotel bills, ledger pages, inventories, household accounts, lists of servants' wages, and accounts showing profits and costs of the publication of Sir Edward Malet's Shifting Scenes.
    - Financial papers, 1824-1907, (1 folder) (Box 27)
  - Clippings Series, 1871-1937
    Clippings regarding Malet family members and their political associates and friends. Includes a few German and Egyptian newspaper clippings.
    - Clippings, 1871-1937and undated (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous Papers Series, 1824-1895and n.d
    Includes drawings, guest list for parties, lists of friends and associates who paid calls, a document granting power of attorney for Sir Alexander Malet to his mother Dame Susanna Malet, and a small sketch of a house plan.
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1824-1895and undated (Box 27)
- Oversize Material
  - Malet Family Subgroup: Sir Henry Charles Eden Malet Album,1834, 1855-1856(1 vol.) (Box 28)
  - Alexander and Edward Malet Subgroup: Printed Material Series (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Queen's Warrant granting Sir Alexander Malet a diplomatic pension, 1867
    - Journal officiel de la République française, 1870 Oct. 18
    - Le Bosphore Egyptien,1883 Aug.31
    - Program and seating scheme for musical event,1885
    - The Pall Mall Gazette, 1887 Feb. 8
    - Printed list of visitors to Windsor Castle, 1891 July 4-8
    - Table arrangement chart for reception of German Emperor at Guildhall, 1891 July 10
    - Berliner Intelligenz Blatt,1894 June25
    - Unidentified seating chart, undated
  - Alexander and Edward Malet Subgroup: Writings Series
    - Prologue to theatrical event, by Sir Edward Malet,1873
  - Alexander and Edward Malet Subgroup: Financial Papers Series
    - Bill and receipt from Hampton's for furnishings for the Berlin Embassy,1887
  - Alexander and Edward Malet Subgroup: Miscellaneous Papers Series
    - Pen and ink drawing by Julian Story,1876